You and I make a lot of decisions every day.
わたしたちは毎日
たくさんの決定をします
Now, some have a little impact on our lives;
小さな決定もあれば
大きな決定もあります
others have a very big impact.
And we can appreciate that we can make
自分で選択し
決定できることに感謝できます
choices and decisions for ourselves.
もし自分で決定できないとしたら
と考えてみてください
Think of how life would be
if you made no decisions for yourself
—someone tells you when to go to bed,
いつ寝るか 何を着るか
どんな仕事をするかを—
they pick out your clothes,
だれかに決められる
としたらどうでしょう？
and they tell you what to do for work.
だれもそうなりたいとは思いません！
Well, none of us would like that!
Jehovah gave each of us free will,
エホバは自分で決定ができるよう—
自由意志という素晴らしい贈り物を
与えてくださいました
and that’s the precious gift
of making choices for ourselves.
エホバがこの贈り物を与えてくださった
理由を考えたことがありますか？
Now, have you ever thought
about why Jehovah gave us this gift?
I mean,
why trust us with free will
わたしたちが時に良くない選択や
決定をしてしまうのに—
when he knew that we could make
bad choices or decisions?
わたしたちを信頼して
与えてくださったのはなぜでしょう？
Well, one powerful reason is love.
1つの大切な理由は 愛です
The only way to give us the gift of love
わたしたちに愛を贈る唯一の手段が
自由意志という贈り物なのです
is also to give us the gift of free will.
The two are tied together.
この2つは密接に関連しています
You really can’t have
one without the other.
片方だけでは成り立ちません
例えば わたしが自分に
“ジョン 愛しています”
For example,
if I programmed my computer
to give me a message
every day at 2:00 p.m.:
“あなたは素晴らしい人です”
というメールを—
“John, I love you.
I think you’re a wonderful guy,”
毎日午後2時に送るよう
セットしたとします
I think there’d be a little something
wrong with me if I thought:
それを見て “ああ ありがたい”
“コンピューターがわたしを愛している”
とは考えません
‘Aw, isn’t that nice?
My computer, it loves me.’
Yeah, love only exists
そうです 愛とは自由意志からのみ
出てくるものなのです
if it comes truly
from a free-will expression.
Now, did Jehovah place
any boundaries on free will?
では エホバは自由意志に
制限を設けられましたか？
Yes.
はい そのことをイスラエル国民への
律法の中に記されました
They were stated in the Law
to the nation of Israel.
And Jesus later repeated them
後にイエスは マタイ 22章37-40節で
そのことに言及されました
at Matthew 22:37-40:
“He said to him:
“イエスは彼に言われた
「『あなたは 心をこめ 魂をこめ—”
“‘“You must love Jehovah your God
with your whole heart
思いをこめてあなたの神
エホバを愛さねばならない』”
“‘“and with your whole soul
and with your whole mind.”
“‘This is the greatest
and first commandment.
“これが最大で第一のおきてです
第二もそれと同様であって こうです”
“‘The second, like it, is this:
“‘“You must love your
neighbor as yourself.”
“『あなたは隣人を自分自身のように
愛さねばならない』”
“‘On these two commandments
“律法全体はこの二つのおきてに
かかっており—”
the whole Law hangs,
and the Prophets.’”
“預言者たちもまたそうです」”
So our use of free will
わたしたちの自由意志は—
神と隣人への愛という境界内で
示されるべきです
has love of God
and love of neighbor
as its boundaries.
Notice, for example,
例えば この絵の中で—
what people are doing
in this picture,
円の境界内にいる人と
外にいる人との違いに注目してください
both inside the circle boundary
and outside.
See, free will allows us to do
自由意志を用いて
絵の中にいる人は何でもできます
any of the things
we see in the picture.
But love of God
and love of neighbor
しかし 神と隣人への愛は
わたしたちを円の外にいる人から遠ざけ—
move us to reject
what’s outside the circle
and choose
to do the kinds of things
円の中にいる人に
良いことを行なうよう動かします
that we see inside the circle.
Now, to stay
within those boundaries,
円の中にいるために エホバは貴重な
知力と良心を与えてくださいましたが—
Jehovah gave us
a marvelous brain
and a built-in conscience,
同時に助けが必要であることも
ご存じです
but he also knows
we need more help.
And that’s why
he also gave us Bible principles
だからこそ エホバは聖書の原則を与えて
その基本的な真理によって—
—basic truths from the Bible
that can help us
to make good decisions.
良い決定ができるように
してくださいました
And it can safely be said
that any decision we face
それで どんな決定も
聖書の原則を導きにできるのです
can be guided
by Bible principles.
Now, our Creator, Jehovah,
knows what’s best for us.
創造者エホバは何が最善かをご存じです
And he also trusts us
to make decisions
わたしたちが聖書の原則によって決定すると
信頼してくださっています
based on Bible principles
because he knows
that when we do that,
そうするなら
わたしたちが幸福になり 満足し—
then we’re really,
truly going to be happy, content,
神と隣人との平和な関係を
楽しめることをご存じなのです
and at peace with him
and with others.
So in review so far:
振り返ってみましょう
Jehovah gave us free will
エホバは自由意志を
与えてくださいました
—that’s the privilege
to make choices for ourselves—
それは 決定をする上での貴重な贈り物です
and he also gave us
Bible principles
また 決定に制限を設けるため
聖書の原則も与えてくださいました
as the boundaries
to our choices.
But making difficult decisions
requires that we train ourselves
難しい決定をする時には—
特に聖書の原則を認め
当てはめなければなりません
to recognize Bible principles
and apply them.
Now let’s read Romans 12:1,
ローマ 12章1節を読んで—
and let’s see how this verse
決定することに関して
何と述べているか考えてみましょう
describes the decision-making process.
“Therefore, I appeal to you
“そのようなわけで 兄弟たち—”
“わたしは神の情けによって
あなた方に懇願します”
“by the compassions of God, brothers,
“to present your bodies
as a living sacrifice,
“あなた方の体を
神に受け入れられる—”
“holy and acceptable to God,
“生きた 聖なる犠牲として
差し出しなさい”
a sacred service
with your power of reason.”
“これがあなた方の
理性による神聖な奉仕です”
So are we using
our “power of reason”
聖書の原則を理解するため
“理性”を働かせていますか？
to understand Bible principles?
For example, young children
例えば
子どもはたくさんの質問をします
ask lots of questions.
But has a child ever asked you:
でも こう聞いたりするでしょうか？
“What happens when I drop a ball?
“ボールを離したらどうなるの？
ペンは？本は？”
a pencil? a book?”
No, they don’t ask that.
そんなことはしません
They know what happens
to anything they drop.
物を離したらどうなるかは
分かっています
It falls down!
当然落ちます！
See, the child doesn’t need
rules for every object
子どもは原則を理解したなら
規則など必要とはしません
but has quickly grasped the principle.
Anything he drops falls down.
手から放した物は落ちます
では 18歳の子が
“このペンを離したらどうなるの？”—
Now,
what if an 18-year-old asked you,
“What’s going to happen
when I drop this pen?”
と聞いたならどうでしょうか？
Well, it’s obvious
he’s not been paying attention
明らかに物理の基本原則を
理解していないことになります
to basic principles of life.
So by us paying attention
to Bible principles,
聖書の原則に注意を払うなら—
we can very quickly see
the pattern
長い規則集など必要とせずに
正しいことを見分け—
of love of God
and love of neighbor
神と隣人への愛を示す方法を
すぐに見極めることができます
and know
the right thing to do
without a long list of rules
for every situation.
Well, how can we train
our “power of reason”?
では どのように
“理性”を働かせますか？
We train it by paying attention
聖書を注意深く読み
研究することによってそうできます
as we read and study the Bible.
Now, we don’t need rules
どんな映画を観るか
どんな音楽を聴くか—
for which movies to watch,
which songs to listen to,
何を着るかに関して
規則は必要ありません
or what clothes we can wear.
If we’re paying attention
when we’re reading the Bible,
聖書を注意深く読むなら
聖書の原則によって良心を訓練し—
we train our conscience
with Bible principles
規則集なしに良い決定を
することができます
so we can make
such decisions
without needing
a long list of rules.
You know,
we could compare our training
“理性”を働かせることを
盲導犬と比較することができます
of our “power of reason”
to a blind person
using a guide dog.
Now, an untrained dog
特に訓練されていない犬でも
視覚障害者にとって助けになります
would be very helpful
to a blind person.
It would bark when others
were around, for example.
例えば 何かがあれば吠えるでしょう
However,
a dog trained
しかし 特別に訓練された盲動犬は
驚くほど有能です
in specific skills
is amazingly helpful.
The dog knows
when to stop at curbs
曲がり角の前で止まったり—
and walk around obstacles
人がぶつからないよう
障害物を避けることもします
that the person
might run their head into.
A guide dog
is also taught a skill called
盲導犬は“賢い不服従”と呼ばれる
特殊な訓練も受けます
“intelligent disobedience.”
And even if the blind person
encourages the dog forward,
視覚障害者が進もうと促しても従わず
危険を避けようとします
it won’t obey,
but it’ll pull
the person back from danger.
Now, it can take a year or more
of training for the dog to learn
盲導犬がそのように有能になるには
1年かそれ以上の時間が必要です
the amazing skills
that are so helpful to a blind person.
Likewise, our raw,
untrained “power of reason”
同様に 訓練されていない“理性”も
幾らか助けにはなります
can help us to a degree.
However, it can be amazing
しかし 時間をかけて訓練するなら
驚くべき働きをします
if we take the time to train it.
Now, here are
three skills that we can use
では “理性”を訓練するのに役立つ
3つのスキルを考えましょう
to train our “power of reason.”
They are illustrating,
例える 分析する バランスを取るです
analyzing,
and balancing.
Now, to consider our first skill,
illustrating,
最初のスキル 例えることについて
人を許すというトピックで考えましょう
let’s use the general topic
of forgiveness.
What Bible principles
could help with forgiveness?
どんな聖書の原則によって
他の人を許すよう助けられますか？
できるだけたくさんの原則や聖句を
思い浮かべてみてください
Please think of as many principles
and scriptures as you can.
Now, if it helps,
you can pause the program now
そして よければビデオをいったん止め—
思い浮かんだ原則を
書き出してみましょう
and write down
the principles that come to mind.
Now, your list
may include principles like these:
その中には マタイ 18章22節の
“77回まで”許しなさい や—
Matthew 18:22 says
to forgive “up to 77 times”;
Proverbs 12:18 says:
箴言 12章18節の
“賢い者たちの舌は人をいやす”—
“The tongue of the wise is a healing”;
and Colossians 3:13 tells us
コロサイ 3章13節の“惜しみなく
許し合いなさい”などがあるでしょう
to ‘forgive one another freely.’
Now, the skill
we want to learn is illustrating
今 学んでいるのは例えること—
—creating a mental picture
of an idea or principle
つまり 心の中で聖句の考えや原則の
真の意味と要点を思い浮かべる能力です
to see its real meaning
and impact.
Now, even if we
are not skilled artists,
芸術家ではなくても わたしたちは皆
心の中で思い描くことができます
all of us can and do create
pictures in our minds.
When illustrating,
pay attention to things that are similar
例えを考えるとき 同じものあるいは
似たものにするよう心がけてください
or like the thing
you are trying to visualize.
For example,
if sin is like debt,
例えば 罪が借金であれば
許しはそれを帳消しにするものです
then forgiveness
is like someone canceling the debt.
If a hurtful remark
is like a cut,
感情を傷つけることが
皮膚を切ることならば—
then forgiveness
is like seeing it heal.
許しはそれを治療することです
If sin is like a mark
on a blackboard,
罪が黒板に線を引くことなら
許しはそれを消すことです
forgiveness is like erasing it.
Proverbs 12:18
箴言 12章18節は
例えに関しての良い手本です
is a great example
of using the “like” technique.
“Thoughtless speech
is like the stabs of a sword,
“剣で突き刺すかのように
無思慮に話す者がいる”
but the tongue of the wise
is a healing.”
“しかし 賢い者たちの舌は人をいやす”
Imagine what your skin
would look like
幼いころ傷つけ 出血した所が
今どうなっているか考えてみてください
if you still had
every open cut, bruise,
or bleeding scratch
since childhood.
See, Jehovah
wonderfully designed our body
エホバは自然治癒力という
素晴らしい力を与えてくださいました
to heal such minor cuts
and bruises.
And we can now visualize
how the forgiveness of others
人を許すことによって
感情的に立ち直っていく様を想像できます
helps us to heal emotionally.
Now, learning to illustrate,
or visualize,
では 例えや想像力を
時間をかけて訓練しましょう
takes time and practice.
However, it can be one
of the most powerful skills we use
それは“理性”を働かせることができる
最も強力なスキルの一つです
to train
our “power of reason,”
and it can also be
quite enjoyable.
それは楽しいものとなります
You know,
try at your family worship
家族の崇拝で
一つのトピックから原則を考え—
to take
the principles for a topic
and see
how many similarities,
どれだけ多くの例えや類似点が
思いつくか—
or “likes,”
you can come up with.
やってみるのはいかがでしょう？
Now, granted,
they all won’t be amazing,
それらを発表し合うなら 新たな観点を
発見できて驚かされるかもしれません
but you may be surprised
by the insights
that come from seeing
something from a new perspective.
Well, let’s consider now
our second skill:
では次に 2つ目のスキル
分析することについて考えましょう
analyzing.
Now, analyzing something means
分析するとは—
あるものを“細かいところまで
注意深く調べる”ことです
“examining it carefully in detail.”
And let’s use
the topic of wrong desires.
これを間違った欲望という
トピックで考えてみましょう
Now, in this case,
let’s say that we’ve already found
コロサイ 3章5節の原則について
取り上げてみます
the principle
at Colossians 3:5:
“Deaden, therefore, your body members
that are on the earth
“ですから 淫行 汚れ
性的欲情 有害な欲望—”
“as respects sexual immorality,
uncleanness,
“また強欲
つまり偶像礼拝に関して—”
“uncontrolled sexual passion,
“hurtful desire, and greediness,
“地上にあるあなた方の
肢体を死んだものとしなさい”
which is idolatry.”
Now, what can we learn
from analyzing Colossians 3:5
悪い欲望と闘うよう—
コロサイ 3章5節を
分析することから何を学べますか？
to help when we struggle
with wrong desires?
Again, feel free
to pause the program
こうしたことを考えるために
再びビデオを止めてみてください
if you want some time
to think about it.
Look carefully
at each step outlined.
それぞれの段階を注意深く調べましょう
Did you notice, for example,
what appears to be
罪に至る段階に
どんなことがあるのかお気づきですか？
a reverse order
of the steps leading to sin?
This verse works its way
from sexual immorality
この聖句は淫行に至る
根本原因を明らかにしています
back to the very roots
of the problem.
Now, let’s take each phrase
starting with the last,
最後の文から考えましょう
“greediness, which is idolatry.”
“強欲つまり偶像礼拝”
So, sexual immorality
starts with selfishness,
淫行は自己本位 他の何よりも自分の必要に
貪欲であることから始まります
greedily putting our needs
ahead of anything else.
Next is “hurtful desire.”
次は “有害な欲望”です
Greediness leads to “hurtful desire.”
“強欲”は“有害な欲望”に至ります
It’s like a person
hanging around a bakery,
お金を払えないのに
パン屋の周りで—
smelling the bread and cakes
when he can’t pay for it.
パンやケーキの匂いを
嗅ぐことに似ています
Likewise,
hanging around immoral entertainment
同様に不道徳な娯楽や悪い交わりは—
or bad associates
わたしたちが本来持たないような
“有害な欲望”をかきたてます
can feed “hurtful desire”
for what is not ours.
Next is listed
“uncontrolled sexual passion.”
次は “性的欲望”です
So “hurtful desire”
has now turned from an idea
“有害な欲望”は それを満たすことが
できる機会を探すよう—
into a strong emotion
of passion,
強い感情的な欲望に変わります
causing one
to look for an opportunity
to fulfill the desire.
Next, “uncleanness.”
続いて “汚れ”
The previous steps have now led
to inappropriate physical conduct
この段階で
他の人との不適切な関係に至ります
with another person.
Finally, “sexual immorality”
—serious sin.
最後に重大な罪である“淫行”です
Sexual immorality
has occurred between persons
淫行は結婚関係外で起こります
that are not married
to one another.
So analyzing Colossians 3:5
コロサイ 3章5節を分析して—
悪い欲望を育てるのではなく
除くよう助けられます
can really help us to eliminate,
not stimulate, wrong desires.
And we can see
how important it is
それをすぐに捨て去ることの
重要性も分かります
to get rid
of wrong desires immediately.
It’s easier
to walk away from sin
前の段階であればあるほど
罪から離れるのは容易になります
when we’re still in the early stages,
rather than later.
So we need
to practice the skill
of not simply
just reading scriptures
聖句をただ読むのではなく
学んだことを生かして分析しましょう
but analyzing them
たくさんの調査用の道具を用いて—
until we’ve learned
all that we can.
And we can use
the many research tools we have
役立ちそうなコメントや適用を
見つけることができます
to find valuable comments
and application.
Now, let’s consider our third
では 最後の3つ目のスキルを
考えましょう
and final skill: balancing.
バランスを取る です
And to do that,
アルコールの用い方という
トピックで考えましょう
let’s use a question
on the topic of alcohol.
What Bible principles
could help a couple to decide
結婚する2人が披露宴で
アルコールを出すかどうかを決める際—
whether to serve alcohol
at their wedding?
どんな聖書の原則が役立ちますか？
What principles and scriptures
do you think would help them
バランスの取れた決定をするため
どんな聖句や原則を思い浮かべますか？
make a balanced decision?
Again, you’re welcome
to pause the program
再びビデオを止め 思い浮かんだ原則や
調べた点を書き出してみましょう
if you’d like to write down
what comes to mind
or to research something.
Now, your list probably has
some of these principles.
挙げられた原則は
次のようなものかもしれません
At John 2:9,
Jesus made wine for a wedding.
ヨハネ 2章9節でイエスが
水をぶどう酒に変えられたことです
However,
1 Corinthians 6:10 says
しかしコリント第一 6章10節には—
that ‘drunkards
will not inherit the Kingdom.’
“大酒飲みは神の王国を受け継がない”
ともあります
And 1 Corinthians 10:31, 32 says:
また コリント第一 10章31, 32節には—
“Whether you are eating or drinking . . . ,
“食べるにしても 飲むにしても—”
do all things for God’s glory”
“すべての事を
神の栄光のためにしなさい”
and to “keep from becoming
causes for stumbling.”
“つまずきのもととならないように”
ともあります
Now,
it doesn’t seem
たった1つの原則からは
答えを引き出すことはできないようです
that any one principle
provides the answer.
The couple could simply say:
2人は “イエスがそうされたんだから—”
“Well, Jesus served wine at a wedding,
so we can too.”
“披露宴でアルコールを出してもよい”
と言うかもしれません
However, there’s really more
to it than that, isn’t there?
しかし 本当にそれだけでしょうか？
It’s clear that a balance
バランスを取って
すべての原則を考えることが必要です
of all these Bible principles
is needed.
Will relatives
or others be there
出席者の中に
酩酊しやすい人がいますか？
who might be prone
to overdrinking?
Would serving alcohol bother
the conscience of many present
地元の習慣や考え方により
兄弟たちの良心が異なりますか？
because of local customs
and feelings about alcohol?
It’s often the case
when making decisions
決定を下す時は幾つかの原則について
バランスを取って考えて—
that we need to balance
several Bible principles,
自分に有利な1つの原則だけで
決定してはなりません
not taking any one principle solely
on its own merit.
Jehovah expects us
to use our “power of reason”
エホバはわたしたちが
“理性”を働かせ—
バランスを取って原則を考えて
決定するよう望んでおられます
to balance Bible principles
and make good decisions.
Ecclesiastes 7:16-18
バランスに関して
伝道の書 7章16-18節は—
良い教訓を与えています
gives us good advice
about being balanced.
“Do not be overly righteous,
“義に過ぎる者となってはならない”
“また 自分を過度に
賢い者としてはならない”
“nor show yourself excessively wise.
“どうして自分の身に
荒廃をもたらしてよいであろうか”
“Why should you bring ruin to yourself?
“邪悪に過ぎる者であってはならない”
“Do not be excessively wicked,
nor be foolish.
“また 愚かな者となるな”
“Why should you die before your time?
“自分の時でもないのに
どうして死んでよいであろうか”
“It is best to grasp one warning
“一方をつかむことのほうが良いが
他方からも手を引くな”
“without letting go of the other;
for the one who fears God
will heed them both.”
“神を恐れる者はそれらすべてと共に
出て行くからである”
How true.
真理ですね
Such balance between extremes
is often necessary
聖書の原則を当てはめる時—
対照的な2つの間で
バランスを取る必要があります
when we apply
Bible principles.
We need to heed them both,
so to speak.
いわば 両者に注意を払います
We need to balance
all the Bible principles
神と隣人への愛を示す決定をするため—
so we can come
to the decision
全ての聖書の原則のバランスを
取る必要があります
that would show love of God
and love of neighbor.
We could illustrate the balance
between different Bible principles
異なる原則に関して
バランスを取る点で—
この自転車の模型を使って考えましょう
and applying them with this model bike.
マラウイの兄弟から頂いた物です
It was a gift from a brother in Malawi.
Now, a bicycle has
three basic principles of operation:
自転車は3つの基本要素から
なっています
the brakes, the pedals, and the steering.
ブレーキ ペダル ハンドルです
Now, the brakes are really like principles
ブレーキは わたしたちが悪い方向へ
向かうのを食い止める原則のようです
that slow us down
or stop us from doing the wrong thing.
And the pedals are really like the principles
ペダルは神と兄弟姉妹への愛を示すよう
わたしたちを動かす原則のようです
that move us forward
in showing love for Jehovah
and our brothers and sisters.
And the steering is like our free will
ハンドルは エホバを歓ばせる決定を選ぶ
自由意志のようです
to choose a direction in life
that pleases Jehovah.
So making decisions
is like riding a bicycle.
決定は自転車に乗るのに似ています
We have to balance
several Bible principles.
幾つかの聖書の原則を
バランスを取って考えなければなりません
So in review,
振り返ってみましょう
Jehovah gave us free will
エホバは神と隣人への愛という範囲内で
用いられる自由意志と—
to use within the boundaries
of love of God and love of neighbor
and many other fine Bible principles.
多くの聖書の原則を
与えてくださいました
Making difficult decisions requires
that we train our “power of reason”
難しい決定をするときには
“理性”を働かせ—
to recognize Bible principles
and apply them.
原則を考え 適用しましょう
And we discussed
how to train
理性を働かせるのに役立つ
3つのスキルとは何でしたか？
our power of reason
with the three skills:
illustrating,
例える 分析する バランスを取る です
analyzing,
and balancing.
どんなことに直面するとしても—
So no matter what decisions
you are faced with,
we encourage you:
“聖書の原則によって導かれるように”
していきましょう
“Let Bible principles guide you.”